<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Plants on vknabel</title><link>https://vknabel.com/tags/plants/</link><description>Recent content in Plants on vknabel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Valentin Knabel</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vknabel.com/tags/plants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Queen of Anthuriums: Warocqueanum</title><link>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-05-25-the-queen-of-anthuriums-warocqueanum/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-05-25-the-queen-of-anthuriums-warocqueanum/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most iconic species of Anthurium is undoubtedly the queen of Anthuriums: the Warocqueanum. With its long, tapering, and often dark leaves, especially adult specimens know how to make a grand impression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The leaves of the Anthurium Warocqueanum can reach a length of over one meter. In this case, they are 65cm.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="caring-for-the-warocqueanum"&gt;Caring for the Warocqueanum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our queen hails from the rainforests of Colombia and naturally occurs in both the humid lowlands and highlands. This relatively broad range of altitudes makes it somewhat less demanding compared to other members of its kind. With proper care, it is undemanding and can tolerate occasional dry stress, as long as there is no new leaf or bloom on the way. It requires slightly higher humidity than other Anthuriums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its thick and robust-looking leaves, you should maintain a constant humidity level of over 50%. Otherwise, it can quickly suffer cosmetic leaf damage. Generally, the plant needs more time than usual to adjust to new conditions, so these should be kept relatively constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Warocqueanum-single-leaf.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding substrate, the Warocqueanum does not have extraordinary requirements for Anthuriums and can be easily kept in semi-hydroponics. As with all Anthuriums, you should use high-quality, airy substrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="personal-experience"&gt;Personal Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I acquired my Warocqueanum, it has been kept under artificial light in a terrarium with humidity usually between 60 and 70%. I have had no problems with root rot or pests, even when other plants in the terrarium were affected. When the humidity dropped too much, there was often leaf damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Warocqueanum-new-leaf.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new leaves of the Warocqueanum start off in a dark green.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my Anthuriums grow faster, but they usually produce smaller leaves. Over time, the Warocqueanum lives up to its name and rules the terrarium with its enormous leaves. It can’t grow much larger due to space constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the leaves of my plant reached a size of about 40cm, it slowly started to bloom. Since I wanted to avoid the stress of seeds and flowers, and because the new leaf was more important to me, I usually removed the flowers or just collected the pollen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hybrids"&gt;Hybrids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the Warocqueanum belongs to the large section Cardiolonchium and thus has many potential hybrids. I don’t have larger specimens yet, but I do have a few candidates with potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Warocqueanum-Esmeralda.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Warocqueanum ‚Esmeralda‘&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Warocqueanum-Esmeralda-x-Dark.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Warocqueanum ‚Esmeralda‘ x ‚Dark‘&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Overview of the Philodendron Malay Gold</title><link>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-02-10-overview-of-the-philodendron-malay-gold/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-02-10-overview-of-the-philodendron-malay-gold/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Featuring bright green to golden leaves with hints of red, the Philodendron Malay Gold is a classic representative of its kind – just brighter. For those who appreciate the color but not necessarily the growth form, alternatives such as Philodendron Hederaceaum ‚Lemon Lime‘ (a.k.a. Scandens) or Epipremnum Aureum ‚Neon‘ are available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Malay-Gold-bright-leaves.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New leafs are bright and yellow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New leaves emerge neon yellow and gradually turn greener over time, maintaining a relatively light hue. The leaf stems, especially at the base, showcase a reddish tint. The more light it receives, the more intense the coloring becomes. The leaves have rounded bases, lack the typical „ears,“ and do not grow particularly large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Malay-Golden-dark-leaves.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Older leafs gradually darken.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="care"&gt;Care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most Philodendrons, the Malay Gold is exceptionally robust. The advantage of easily assessing the lighting conditions based on new leaves provides timely feedback after relocation. While it cannot thrive in as low light conditions as some of its counterparts, it does not demand an exceptionally bright location either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Malay-Gold-tall.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four substantial Malay Gold plants in a single container. Fresh leaves exhibit a lighter hue and gradually darken over time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It simply wants to grow tall and fast, with an inherent upward trajectory. Although the stem is typically broader than that of a Melanochrysum, a support structure becomes necessary at a certain height. While it would likely accept a moss pole, it is not strictly necessary.
Personal Experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Malay Gold has adorned various corners of my home: in winter on the south side, centrally located, on the east and west sides directly by the window. Maintaining humidity levels between 30% and 60%. Notably, there were no significant issues in any of these placements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has even stood directly next to the open balcony door in summer and fall, welcoming thrips that occasionally find their way in. While a mild infestation occurred, it caused no substantial harm. Other pests have never been a concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Malay-Gold-and-Epipremnum-Aureum-Neon.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the same pot, serving as a small contrasting companion, an Epipremnum Aureum ‚Neon‘ is thriving as a sublet. It flourishes better in this shared space than when grown alone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given its size, the water requirements for our plant are relatively modest. Thanks to its determination to grow upward, its space requirements are also manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="propagation"&gt;Propagation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s needless to say that propagating a Philodendron is at best a challenging task. The Malay Gold is no exception and is most effectively propagated through cuttings. The advantage lies in its ability to develop aerial roots even in moderate humidity conditions, facilitating an effortless rooting process for cuttings that swiftly establish themselves as independent plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Malay-Gold-two-years-ago.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My plant two years ago.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item><item><title>Of Velvet and Silver: the Syngonium Wendlandii</title><link>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-02-03-of-velvet-and-silver-the-syngonium-wendlandii/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-02-03-of-velvet-and-silver-the-syngonium-wendlandii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Syngonium Wendlandii is truly something special. With its deep green, velvety leaves, a silver stripe in the middle, and a relatively compact size, it sets itself apart from its counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, there is also the Syngonium Rayii, which, however, requires higher humidity but rewards with significantly darker leaves.
A Syngonium Wendlandii on a moss pole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaves themselves feel slightly velvety but also somewhat firmer. In the juvenile form, the leaves are arrow-shaped, and with age, the earlobes separate, transforming the leaf into three parts. This is not unusual for Syngoniums – here, it happens faster and more straightforwardly. However, with increasing leaf size, the silver color diminishes and thins out.
The juvenile leaves are arrow-shaped, as in other young Syngoniums.
The adult leaves are three-parted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="care"&gt;Care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With few exceptions, Syngoniums are straightforward and have no special requirements for humidity. This holds true for Wendlandii, despite its velvety leaves. Although the leaves have a silvery sheen, it doesn’t need more light than its counterparts without silver and can thrive in darker locations.
Without high humidity, it won’t root into moss poles. A bamboo stake will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Syngonium-Wendlandii-from-top.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Wendlandii outside of display cases doesn’t necessarily need a moss pole. Below 60 to 70% humidity, too few aerial roots form, risking root rot if the substrate is not airy enough. However, a stake is recommended for a beautiful growth, especially if you desire the three-parted adult leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="personal-experience"&gt;Personal Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Syngonium is positioned by the east window, receiving direct morning sunlight and experiencing slightly cooler temperatures of 18 to 20°C in winter. Even during the height of summer, temperatures rarely exceed 25°C. The humidity usually hovers around 40 to 45%, occasionally dropping to 35%. In the past, I had it in a moss pole setup with humidity maintained at 60 to 70%, and it thrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Syngonium-Wendlandii-Moss-Pole.jpg" alt=""&gt;
However, the moss pole wasn’t necessary, as the plant never embraced it, often leading to overly damp substrate. Despite this, the support structure brought visible delight to the Syngonium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, it proves remarkably robust, enduring various conditions under my care, and certainly does not exhibit diva-like tendencies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="propagation"&gt;Propagation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other Syngoniums, Wendlandii rarely blooms indoors. Thus, propagation through cuttings takes precedence.
It appreciates a support for climbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Syngonium-Wendlandii-juvenile-leaves.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Juvenile arrowheads are found below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Syngonium-Wendlandii-adult-leaves.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adult leaves grace the top.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it grows quickly, branching out from the stem and becoming bushier, pruning is a wise choice. The cutting should then root well. However, more patience is required here compared to many other Syngoniums, as root initiation often takes time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Anthurium Gracile: Care and Propagation</title><link>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-01-31-anthurium-gracile-care-and-propagation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-01-31-anthurium-gracile-care-and-propagation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Those in search of an Anthurium characterized by uncomplicated care will find success with the Anthurium Gracile, and will be rewarded by its affordable price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaves of Anthurium Gracile are bright, thin, and feel somewhat leathery. In ample light, the leaf base can take on a reddish hue. Some cultivated forms also tend to show a reddish coloration on the stem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its compactly growing stem gives it a bushy appearance. As the leaves protrude forward and gently taper towards the tip, the plant becomes quite expansive. Unlike Pallidiflorum and similar „Long-Boys,“ creating a leaf curtain without tilting the pot becomes challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Anthurium Gracile grows compact and has long belted leaves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="care"&gt;Care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comparison the Anthurium Gracile is easy to handle but requires a more aerated substrate due to its fleshy, almost orchid-like roots. This allows it to stay dry longer, reducing the risk of root rot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semi-hydroponics is also a trouble-free alternative to organic substrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The humidity can be slightly lower than for most other Anthurium species. Spider mites have not been an issue, with only a reported incidence of thrips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="personal-experience"&gt;Personal Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cultivated my Gracile almost exclusively in display cases, maintaining humidity between 50% and 80%, and providing artificial light for 12 to 14 hours daily. Despite occasional neglect, it took just under a year to reach the second generation from seeds. During the summer, the room temperature often soared between 20 and 28°C in the evenings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it resides outside the display case and thrives even with 40% humidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spider mites posed no challenge, and I only encountered a thrips infestation. Despite visible leaf damage, the impact on growth was minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="inflorescence"&gt;Inflorescence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthurium Gracile is highly prolific in flowering, typically producing a new bloom with each leaf. Being self-pollinating, no specific action is required for the development of red berries. The inflorescences are unusually located beneath the leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Gracile-inflo-1536x1152.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The flowers of the Anthurium Gracile are unimpressive and usually grow below the leaves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to other species, the berries ripen in just a few weeks rather than several months. Due to the low cost and high frequency of new seedlings, it’s advisable to trim the inflorescences in the long run to avoid unnecessary stress on the plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="crossbreeding"&gt;Crossbreeding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belonging to the Leptanthurium section along with Vittariifolium, Anthurium Gracile has no known other species. However, successful pollination with closely related sections may occur with some luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Gracile-berries-1024x1024.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Five red berries of the Anthurium Gracile.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The berries of the Anthurium Gracile are red and similar sized to the seeds of a Grapefruit. It usually contains 1 or 2 seeds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Gracile-Spadix-with-berries-1024x768.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The spadix and a few berries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Plant Care Guides on the Internet Are Bullshit</title><link>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-01-01-why-plant-care-guides-on-the-internet-are-bullshit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-01-01-why-plant-care-guides-on-the-internet-are-bullshit/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are already many websites offering plant care tips. The articles tend to be very long but contain little relevant information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every plant is described as needing bright, indirect light and as being unable to tolerate root rot or requiring fertilisation in winter. It&amp;rsquo;s as if there are plants that like to rot away! It is often stated that houseplants need increased humidity. By how much? 50%? 80%? The exact specification is often missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and by the way&amp;hellip; This beautiful plant is the perfect starter plant for you. It only costs $50 and will attract spider mites if it is not cared for properly. Completely altruistic, of course. Shops and websites with affiliate links or advertising are simply not reliable or independent sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Gloriosum-2048x1536.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For example, a Philodendron Gloriosum is prone to spider mites when humidity is too low.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-matters"&gt;What matters?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every plant is unique and grows in a unique environment: yours. Every tip for caring for a plant comes from someone with different watering habits, substrate and lighting conditions. Humidity, air circulation, temperature and fertilisation can all be different, too. Even the water probably has a completely different hardness level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Various-cuttings-in-a-jar.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various cuttings in water: Philodendron Brandtianum &amp;amp; Birkin, Monstera Adansonii &amp;lsquo;Swedish Ghost&amp;rsquo;, Rhapidophora Tetrasperma, Epipremnum Cebu Blue and an Anthurium Rubrinervium.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes it impossible to make suggestions that are applicable everywhere—or that make sense. That&amp;rsquo;s why you see the same information everywhere. Nevertheless, there are differences. These must be pointed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-were-different"&gt;How we&amp;rsquo;re different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than resorting to the same old clichés, we compare different plants and assume that you already have some. No bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read our care tips for anthuriums and compare them with other arum plants, such as alocasias and philodendrons. We also provide profiles or portraits of individual species for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Philodendron-Billietiae-1536x2048.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Philodendron billietiae on a climbing stick.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let&amp;rsquo;s compare &lt;a href="https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-01-31-anthurium-gracile-care-and-propagation/"&gt;Anthurium gracile&lt;/a&gt; with other anthuriums. If you already have experience of caring for anthuriums, we only need to briefly address their special features. This will also give you a quick overview of the plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most species grow differently and can be displayed in various ways. If a plant has an unusual growth habit, we will mention that, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Gracile-overview.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For example, an &lt;a href="https://vknabel.com/posts/2024-01-31-anthurium-gracile-care-and-propagation/"&gt;Anthurium gracile&lt;/a&gt; with burns on its leaves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We only write about our own plants, not random or trendy ones. If the plant has a yellow leaf, this will be included in the photo. There will be content about common plants, as well as lesser-known plants and individual hybrids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Veitchii-768x1024.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anthurium Veitchii Jungpflanze&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Besseae-aff-768x1024.jpeg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Anthurium Besseae aff&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src="https://vknabel.com/images/aroid.garden/Anthurium-Villenaonarum-x-Besseae-768x1024.jpeg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Anthurium Villenaorum x Besseae&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>